Guide to the Jack Randall Crawford Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jack Randall Crawford papers
1889-1951
MS 153
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
13
(37 boxes)
Correspondence, diaries, an autobiography, writings, research notes, and teaching materials of Jack Randall Crawford. Also included are a small amount of papers belonging to Dorothy Gabain, Crawford's second wife. The largest part of the papers is made up of plays, fiction and literary criticism, both published and unpublished, written by Crawford. Also included are lecture notes and texts and students papers reflecting his teaching career at Yale University (1909-1946).
Crawford, Jack Randall, 1878-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dorothy Crawford, 1960 and 1972.
Biographical / Historical
Jack Randall Crawford: author, educator; professor of English at Yale University, 1909-1946; professor emeritus, 1946-1968; author of novels and studies of literature.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, diaries, an autobiography, writings, research notes, and teaching materials of Jack Randall Crawford. Also included are a small amount of papers belonging to Dorothy Gabain, Crawford's second wife. The largest part of the papers is made up of plays, fiction and literary criticism, both published and unpublished, written by Crawford. Also included are lecture notes and texts and students papers reflecting his teaching career at Yale University (1909-1946).
Authors, American; Literature -- History and criticism; Students; Theater; Autobiographies; Diaries; Authors; Educators; Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949; Bingham, Hiram, 1875-1956; Blanshard, Brand, 1892-1987; Brooke, Tucker, 1883-1946; Crawford, Dorothy; Crawford, Jack Randall, 1878-; Griswold, Alfred Whitney, 1906-1963; Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1856-1930; Haight, Gordon Sherman; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Nettleton, George Henry, 1874-1959; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943; Rogers, James Grafton, 1883-1971; Seymour, Charles, 1885-1963; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of English
- Inventory, 1878-1968
  Scope and Contents
  Associate Professor of English, Yale University
  Original fiction, scholarly discussion, various notes, and lectures of Jack Randall Crawford are contained here in 25 boxes.
  - Prose
    - "To those who are left, to my children who do not know these things, and to the memory of those more numerous who have gone." -- an autobiographical work; three copies are present. Each copy has its own variant. (Box 1)
    - For the Most Fair (a fictional work - one copy) (Box 1)
    - The Philosopher's Murder Case (Box 2)
      General
      Includes two incongruous manuscripts, only one of which is complete.
    - Growth of English Comedy (Box 3)
    - Elizabethan Translations (Box 3)
    - Also an incomplete and untitled manuscript (Chps II - XXVII) (Box 3)
    - Albert Enters the World (Box 3a)
    - Deer Harbor (Chps 9-13) (Box 3a)
    - England (Chps 1-5) (Box 3a)
    - The Garden City (Act I) (Box 3a)
    - The Magic of the Hills (Box 3a)
    - Analysis of Manuel Komroff's Coronet (Box 3a)
    - Discussion of Joan Lowell's Cradle of the Deep (Box 3a)
    - Discussion of John Rathbone Oliver's Foursquare, The Story of a Foursquare Life (Box 3a)
    - A paper on Samuel Butler (Box 3a)
    - Report by JRC to the movie owners of Abie's Wild Irish Rose (Box 3a)
    - Review of the Wall of Glass by Amabel Williams-Ellis (Box 3a)
    - Great Moments in History, McCormick and the Reaper (Box 3a)
    - The Ghost of Hamlet (historical approach to the dramatic ghost) (Box 4)
  - Plays
    - Back to Nature (Box 4)
    - Death of a Soldier of Fortune (Box 4)
    - The Norton System (2 copies) (Box 4)
    - The Thursday Club (Box 4)
    - Worcester Pagean t (Box 4)
    - Fruits of Culture by Leo Tolstoi - adapted by JRC for the Drama (Box 4)
    - Fragment of a play, Act II: possibility that it might be Fruits of Culture (Box 4)
    - Gay and Transient (2 copies) (Box 5)
    - This Dark World (3 episodes--incomplete) (Box 6)
    - The Postmistress of Rocky Park (Box 6)
    - Sister Anne (Box 6)
    - Tam Linn (Box 6)
    - The Joy Ride (Lee Wilson Dodd--co-author) (Box 6)
    - Senlac (2 copies; each is five acts) (Box 7)
      Awarded the John Addison Porter Prize.
    - Lovely Peggy (with notes) -- one copy of the three acts in hardcover notebooks (Box 8)
    - The Bezsemenoffs (Box 9)
    - The Glass House (first and third copies complete; acts three and four of another copy) (Box 9)
    - Lovely Peggy (2 copies-- one complete in one volume; the other bound in three volumes.) (Box 9)
    - At the End of the Passage (Box 10)
    - Dante (2 copies) (Box 10)
    - The Dissapearing Flat (Box 10)
    - Nichevo (Box 10)
    - The Quest of Helen (Box 10)
    - A Shavian Parody (Box 10)
    - Zelma (Box 10)
    - Jack Randall Crawford, co-author:
      - The Bishop's Wife (F.C.Constable) (Box 10)
      - The Lady of Ischia (Gladys Unger) (Box 10)
    - Jack Randall Crawford, adaptor
      - Behind the Beyond by Stephen Leacock (Box 10)
      - Gringoire by Theodore de Barrville (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous
      - fragments of two plays, probably by JRC (Box 10)
      - Program: Pilgrim Tercentenary Pageant (JRC, director) (Box 10)
      - Notes re: Pre-Tudor Moralities (Box 10)
      - Notes re: The Marco Plays (Box 10)
  - Notebooks
    - Hamlet (2 notebooks) (Box 11)
    - The Pursuit of Happiness -- prose work (Box 11)
    - Notebooks in re:
      - Dramatics (Box 12)
      - Development of the English novel (Box 12)
      - Literary subjects (Box 12)
      - French epic poetry (Box 12)
      - Gunnery (JRC, former instructor) (Box 13)
      - Literary subjects (Box 13)
      - Stage and drama (Box 13)
      - Criticism (Box 13)
      - Grade book (1935--second term) (Box 13)
      - Character of Drayton Fisher (personality presumably to be used by JRG in his writings) (Box 13)
  - Notes
    - Notes on drama and the history of drama (Box 14)
    - Notes on drama and the history of drama (Box 15)
    - Notes on literary forms and schools. realism, naturalism, romanticism, etc. (Box 16)
    - Manual on the short story and composition; also Knights of Columbus Home Education Study by JRC. (Box 17)
    - Notes on psychology and psychological interpretations; also tragedy, comedy, poetry etc. (Box 18)
    - Notes on bibliography and reading lists (Box 19)
    - Notes on bibliography -- including "What to Read in English Literature" (Box 20)
    - Notes on criticism (Box 21)
    - Notes on criticism and personalities in drama (Box 22)
    - Notes for lectures and texts for various lectures (Box 23)
    - Notes on creation and expression: miscellaneous material included (Box 24)
      - "The Dramatist's Point of View" (Box 24)
      - "Attitude of an Artist" (Box 24)
    - Filing drawer: catalogue cards on Hamlet (Box 25)
    - Filing drawer: catalogue cards on the theory of the drama (Box 26)
  - Plays and prose
    - You Never Know Your Luck (Box 27)
    - The Faithless Columbine (2 copies) (Box 27)
    - Hart, of Africa (Box 27)
    - The Crater's Edge (Box 27)
    - I Walked in Arden (a rather confused and incoherent compilation of manuscripts which hopefully belong to "Arden") (Box 27)
    - His Enemy-The Friend (Box 27)
    - Cupid and Psyche by John Jay Chapman (JRC's stage notes are integrated in the text.) (Box 27)
    - The Pageant of Suffield, Conn. (Box 27)
    - The Pageant of the Peddie Institute and the Community of Highstown, New Jersey (Box 27)
    - The Joy Ride (a synopsis of the four act play) (Box 27)
    - Sandfield's Laboratory (story) Cases I, II, III (Box 27)
    - Political Fables (Box 27)
    - Marcel Schwob's Mimes (Box 27)
    - one untitled novel (20 chapters) by JRC (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous Crawford work
    - Report of Chief Reader (JRC) of Comprehensive Exams, 1928 June, 1934 June (Box 28)
    - "Report of the reading of the comprehensive English books for the new plan candidates" (Box 28)
    - Coviello - a commedia dell'arte in two acts (Box 28)
    - Do Not Do To Others by Roberto Braceo - translated and adapted by JRC. (Box 28)
    - After Many Years (one act) (Box 28)
    - Polly Twaddles [The reader is required to fill in all the dialogue blanks himself.] (Box 28)
    - Father Duval (a synopsis of the play) (Box 28)
    - Scenario (a synopsis of the play) (Box 28)
    - review of The Revolutionary Playwright's Handbook by G.B. Shaw; Ulysses - a drama by Stephen Phillips (Box 28)
    - The Gift of Stone (4 pages) by JRC (Box 28)
    - Mesopotamia (Box 28)
    - Entertaining a Visitor (Box 28)
    - Ancassin and Nicolete (Box 28)
    - One page papers written for Professors Phelps and Nettleton (Box 28)
    - Poems and limericks written for amusement (Box 28)
    - 6 untitled short papers (5-6 pages) (Box 28)
    - 4 unidentified plays in various stages of survival (Box 28)
    - One battered and coverless notebook filled with personal sketches and personal experiences of JRC. (Box 28)
    - Constitution of Chi Delta Theta, honary literary society of Yale University, founded Nov. 6, 1821 (Box 28)
    - Memorandum of interview with JRC re Overton matter. Also handwritten note of Preident Hadley re Overton. (Box 28)
    - Readings for Timothy Dwight Christmas Party, 1948 (Box 28)
    - Report on books read for Professor Nettleton's Drama Course - date (Box 28)
    - Sheffield Scientific School - outline of Sophomore English, 1921-1922 (Box 28)
    - Speech given by JRC to the New England Association of Teachers of English, 1927 December (Box 28)
  - Correspondence and reviews and articles by/about JRC
    - Correspondence
      - A-D
        - Pres. Angell to JRC (2), 1929 (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - George Pierce Baker (3), 1925-1929 (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - Hiram Bingham to JRC, 1925 (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - Brand Blanchard to JRC, 1949 (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - Tucker Brooke to JRC (3), 1937-1946 (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - Walter Ceerley, Jr.('44) to JRC, 1944 (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - Malcolm W. Davis to JRC, 1929 (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - W.C. DeVane to JRC, 1945 (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - Lee Wilson Dodd to JRC, 1922 (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - Norman V. Donaldson to JRC, 1951 (Box 29, Folder 1)
      - E-K
        - Robert French to JRC, 1946 (Box 29, Folder 2)
        - Fred Godley to JRC (Box 29, Folder 2)
        - A.W.Griswold to JRC, 1950 (Box 29, Folder 2)
        - JRC - A. T. Hadley (3), 1917-1918 (Box 29, Folder 2)
        - Gordon S. Haight to JRC (2), 1945-1949 (Box 29, Folder 2)
        - Bernhard Knollenberg to JRC, 1941 (Box 29, Folder 2)
      - L-N
        - Carl Lohman to JRC: official certificates (Box 29, Folder 3)
        - JRC - G. H. Nettleton (5), 1926-1944 (Box 29, Folder 3)
      - O-T
        - David Potter to JRC (Box 29, Folder 4)
        - Fred Pottle to JRC, 1944 (Box 29, Folder 4)
        - William Lyon Phelps to JRC (2), 1911, 1922 (Box 29, Folder 4)
        - James Grafton Rogers to JRC (2), 1938, 1942 (Box 29, Folder 4)
        - Jim Rogers '25S (nephew of above), 1946 (Box 29, Folder 4)
        - Charles Seymour (Provost) to JRC, 1937 (Box 29, Folder 4)
        - Charles Seymour (Pres.) to JRC (22), 1942-1945 (Box 29, Folder 4)
        - Anson Phelps Stokes to JRC, 1918 (Box 29, Folder 4)
        - Kenneth Sprang to JRC, 1942 (Box 29, Folder 4)
        - Day Tuttle to JRC, 1956 (Box 29, Folder 4)
        - C. H. Warren to JRC (3), 1928, 1938, 1946 (Box 29, Folder 4)
      - U-Z and personal (Box 29, Folder 5-5A)
      - Correspondence transferred from Miscellaneous Manuscripts
        - John M. Burke to Mrs. T.C. Crawford, 1903 (Box 29, Folder 6)
        - Herbert Hoover to JRC, 1946 (Box 29, Folder 6)
        - John Livingston Lowes to JRC, 1921 (Box 29, Folder 6)
        - C. Loval Fraser to JRC (3), Undated (Box 29, Folder 6)
        - Mrs. John A. Logan to Mrs. T. C. (Inez R.) Crawford, 1903 (Box 29, Folder 6)
        - Henry Mayer to JRC (2), 1909 (Box 29, Folder 6)
        - Clifford Odets to JRC, 1935 (Box 29, Folder 6)
        - G. H. Putnam to JRC, 1927 (Box 29, Folder 6)
        - Marshall P. Wilder to JRC, 1903 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Reviews and Articles
      - Newpaper clippings of JRC's reviews (Box 29, Folder 7)
      - Programs of JRC's productions (largely from the Dartmouth summer sessions 1915-1918) (Box 29, Folder 7)
      - Program for Waterbury, Conn. pageant - JRC, director, 1924 (Box 29, Folder 7)
      - Various papers and magazines with articles by/about JRC (Box 29, Folder 8)
      - 2 issues of Creative Reading (JRC - author and co-author) (Box 29, Folder 9)
      - University of Southern California catalogues for the 1936 summer session. JRC's courses listed and described (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - Longer creative works
    - Untitled novel - published in Canada. one copy, typed (Box 30)
    - Notebooks, two hardcover: dated June and September 1910, but entries continue to 1951-1952, 1910-1952 (Box 30)
      Contains sketches, notes for classes, and preliminary exam and test questions.
  - Diaries
    - 1889 November-1890 April (Box 31)
    - 1890 April-1891 March (Box 31)
    - 1891 March-September (Box 31)
    - 1891 September-1893 (Box 31)
    - 1896 (Box 31)
    - 1897 (Box 31)
    - 1899 January-March (Box 31)
  - Academic notebooks
    - Essay on Class of 1901, "Upper Middle First" at Berkeley School, Princeton, Undated (Box 31)
    - English notes, 1898 September (Box 31)
    - Sophomore Year, 2nd Semester
      - Chemistry (Box 31)
      - Chemistry (Box 31)
    - Junior Year, 1st Semester
      - Chemistry 3 (Box 31)
      - English Philology and Elizabethan Dramatists (Box 31)
      - Organic Chemistry (Box 31)
      - Jurisprudence and Politics (Box 31)
      - History of the Renaissance (Box 31)
      - English Literature 5 (Box 31)
    - Junior Year, 2nd Semester
      - Economics (Box 31)
      - Psychology (Box 31)
      - Geology (Box 31)
      - Logic (Box 31)
      - Political Science (Box 31)
      - History of the Religious Wars (Box 32)
      - History of Philosophy (Box 32)
    - Senior Year, 1st Semester
      - Art 3 (Box 32)
      - Sociology (Box 32)
      - American Literature (Box 32)
      - History of Modern Philosophy (Box 32)
      - Constitutional Government (Box 32)
      - History of the Reformation (Box 32)
    - Senior Year, 2nd Semester
      - Gothic Architecture (Box 32)
      - History of the Tudors (Box 32)
      - Art 2 (Box 32)
      - British Poetry of the 19th Century (Box 32)
      - Interpretation of Literature (Box 32)
      - Metaphysics (Box 32)
      - History of Philosophy (Box 32)
    - Chemistry notes, 1904 (Box 32)
    - Notes on steel-making, 1907 (Box 32)
    - 19th Century European Politics. Also some verse (Yale), 1908 October (Box 32)
    - Dramatic Composition. Contains lyric "Do You Remember" (1951), 1910 Sep, 1951 (Box 32)
    - "Durham's Course" seemingly on 18th Century Philosophy. Also includes "Along these Lines," an assembly of clichés compiled from "much reading of fiction", 1910 October (Box 32)
    - Contemporary Drama, including a "Theater Record" and a "Yale diary", 1910 October (Box 32)
    - English Literature Outlines, 1911 August (Box 32)
    - Old English. Mostly containing short sketches, 1912 July (Box 32)
    - Some notes on steel making, mostly notes from a French course., Undated (Box 32)
  - Writings and notes
    - Untitled fictional work and essay "Chemical Theory Simplified", Undated (Box 33)
    - Travel Sketches, essays "Hypnotism and Crime" and "Curvature in Greek Architecture", 1899 July (Box 33)
    - Many short sketches, Circa 1900 (Box 33)
    - Essays "The Pre-Raphaelites", "A Plea for Romanticism", "Callow Pessimism". Story "On the Emperor's Staff." Essay "Notes on Brotherhood", "Analysis of a Story", story and play suggestions, a translated poem and Act I of a play "Between Anecdotes", 1900 October (Box 33)
    - Short play "The Turkey Gobbler", sketch of a novel, "Ulysses" by Stephen Phillips (an essay on it), story "The Emperor of a Republic," sketch "The Girl in the Raglan" and some verse, 1901 November (Box 33)
    - 1901 March (Box 33)
    - Story "A Legend from the North", one act comedy "The A.D.A.", some verse and sketches for stories and plays. (Box 33)
    - Essay "Religion" and a translation, Act I of Maeterlinck's "Momma Vanna", 1902 July (Box 33)
    - Sketches "A Coaching Trip" and "Smith", ideas for short stories, "The Rainbow Knight," a play, a passenger list and essay "Youth's Idleness", 1903 January (Box 33)
    - Magazine, Ainslee's, in which Crawford's article "Bridge" appears, 1903 October (Box 33)
    - "Sandfield's Laboratory," a story, 1903 October (Box 33)
    - "Sandfield's Laboratory", essay "Audiences 170 Years Ago", verses and sketches for plays, Circa 1904 (Box 33)
    - Seven Spades to Death, manuscripts of a murder mystery, Undated (Box 33)
    - Albert Enters the World, a novel, chapters 6-12 inclus, Undated (Box 33)
    - Albert Enters the World, novel, chapters 13 to end, Undated (Box 33)
    - To My Children and Grandchildren, an autobiography, Undated (Box 33)
    - essay "The Growth of English Comedy", and part of a play "The Impostor", Undated (Box 33)
    - essay "The Growth of English Comedy" (continued), Undated (Box 33)
    - essay "The Growth of English Comedy II" and sources for this essay. Includes notes and parts of play "The Company Promoter", adapted part of play "La Petíte Fundtionnaire", a European travel essay, a sketch "Mesopotamia", Undated (Box 33)
    - Notes on medieval drama and on cement-making, Undated (Box 33)
    - Packet of letters and two stories, "The Rambler", and "After Five Years." (Box 33)
  - Plays
    - "Lucia d'Andrea", a comedy by K Dove, translated and adapted by J.R. Crawford, and an untitled play by Crawford, 1904 June (Box 34)
    - Notes for plays "The President and the Anarchist", "Senlac", "Father Vangu", notes on English drama, booklists, notes on metallurgical processes, 1906 July (Box 34)
    - Two plays, "The Professor's Discovery" and "Starvation", 1908 August (Box 34)
    - Play "The Thursday Club", Acts I and II, Undated (Box 34)
    - Part of Crawford's adaptation of "La Petie Functionnaire" by Alfred Capus. Essay "Notes on Art in Life", Undated (Box 34)
    - Play "The Promoter", parts of act I, Undated (Box 34)
    - Plays "Breaking the Colt (?)" and "Last Memory Play", some notes on metallurgy, Undated (Box 34)
    - Manuscripts of "Senlac", five act play, and "The Begsemenoffs", by Maxims Gorky, translated by Crawford. Also written version of acts II and III of "Begsemenoffs" and some press notices of this play, undated (Box 34)
    - Part of an untitled play and notes on metallurgy, Undated (Box 34)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Some notes on Princeton life, 1898 June (Box 34)
    - Book "The Answer of Adam" by H.N. McCracken, 1908 December (Box 34)
    - Scrapbook of press clippings, Undated (Box 34)
    - Address book, Undated (Box 34)
    - Memos from Keystone Electric Co., Circa 1902 (Box 34)
    - Memos from Keystone Electric Co., Circa 1902 (Box 34)
  - Dorothy Gabain
    - Practical Chemistry, 1907-1908 (Box 34)
    - Physical Chemistry (Box 34)
    - Chemistry (vol. II), 1907 November (Box 34)
    - Chemistry (vol. III) (Box 34)
    - Chemistry (Box 34)
    - Chemistry (Box 34)
    - Chemistry (Box 34)
    - Biology (Box 35)
    - German (Box 35)
    - History (French) (Box 35)
    - English (Shakespeare) Lit. (Box 35)
    - History (English) (Box 35)
    - History (English) (Box 35)
    - Laboratory Notes (Box 35)
  - Articles for the Daily Princetonian and other publications, 1898-1902 (Box 36)
  - Diary, 1897-1898 (Box 36)
  - Twelve pages from diary, 1898 February 3-19 (Box 36)